{"tossups": [{"question": "Brigade 2506 was a military group trained by this organization in an attempt to bring the Democratic Revolutionary Front to power in one country. A 1947 National Security Act created this organization which was preceded by the Office of Strategic Services. The Bay of Pigs Invasion, as well as several attempts to assassinate Castro, was planned by, for ten points, what federal agency responsible for gathering overseas intelligence?", "answer": "<b> CIA</b> (accept<b> Central Intelligence Agency</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Louis XV demanded that this monarch renounce Francis I\u2019s claims to the Duchy of Lorraine in favor of the deposed Stanislaw I of Poland. In the Treaty of Aachen, this monarch was forced to cede Parma to Bourbon Spain. This daughter of Charles VI fought a war with Frederick II which resulted in Prussia seizing control of Silesia. The Pragmatic Sanction of 1713 allowed the ascension of, for ten points, what Empress of Austria?", "answer": "Empress<b> Maria Theresa</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1957, Philip Siekevitz popularized a teaching tool regarding this organelle. This organelle names a theorized \u201cEve\u201d figure who lived 150 thousand years ago; that figure is the matrilineal ancestor of all modern humans, because this organelle contains DNA typically only inherited from the mother. The Krebs cycle takes place in, for ten points, what organelle that generates ATP and is commonly called the powerhouse of the cell?", "answer": "<b> mitochondria</b> (accept<b> mitochondrion</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "This leader initiated a series of economic reforms as part of Operation Forward. A mass sterilization campaign was carried out by this leader during the 21-month long Emergency. The Smiling Buddha test was authorized by this leader who ordered a raid on the Golden Temple in Amritsar in Operation Blue Star. Two Sikh bodyguards assassinated, for ten points, what Indian Prime Minister, the daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru?", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira<b> Gandhi</b> (prompt on Gandhi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man will supposedly fight both the al-Masih ad-Dajjal and his followers while dressed in yellow garb near Damascus. According to Al-Tabari, this man healed the son of Phillip the Tetrarch and created birds from clay to entertain children. Several Hadith testimonials and the Quran claim that this man was a product of a virgin birth. For ten points, name this penultimate prophet of Islam and son of Maryam who is considered the Messiah of the Old Testament.", "answer": "<b> Isa</b> ibn Maryam (accept<b> Jesus Christ</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This document\u2019s predecessor was revised by the Annapolis Convention. An issue during the drafting of this document was resolved by the Connecticut Compromise. The beginning of this document promises to \u201cPromote the general welfare\u201d and \u201cInsure Domestic Tranquility.\u201d Edmund Randolph and George Mason refused to sign this document until the introduction of a Bill of Rights. For ten points, name this document, largely written by James Madison, the foundational document of the United States.", "answer": "United States\u201d<b> Constitution</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One example of this musical form was inspired by a cat walking on a harpsichord and was composed by Domenico Scarlatti. Fourteen of these pieces in D minor are labeled \u201cContrapunctus\u201d in a work titled for<em> The Art of</em> [these pieces]. Renaissance music theorist Gioseffo Zarlino contrasted these works and canons in the 16th century. J.S. Bach wrote a D minor organ piece that pairs one of these works with a\u201cToccata.\u201d For ten points, name this type of contrapuntal work that is often paired with a prelude.", "answer": "<b> fugue</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This leader tasked Lot Smith to form a militia and eliminate the Timpanogos. The proposed state of\u201cDeseret\u201d was spearheaded by this man, who lost much of his national credibility following the Mountain Meadows Massacre. This leader banned black men in his clergy, claiming they were sons of Cain. This man took control of a religious group after its founder died in Illinois. The Mormons were led to Utah by, for ten points, what successor of Joseph Smith?", "answer": "Brigham<b> Young</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An expedition led by Gil Eannes, supported by this man, crossed Cape Bojador. For ten points, name this 15th century Portuguese prince whose funding helped start the Age of Discovery.", "answer": "Prince<b> Henry the Navigator</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This colony developed after civilians rejected a 1923 referendum to become the fifth province of South Africa. Leaders of this colony decided to ally with Antonio Salazar to resist the policy of \u201cno independence before majority rule.\u201d This colony issued the Unilateral Declaration of Independence under Ian Smith, sparking a civil war. The Lancaster House Agreement ended the Bush War in, for ten points, what British colony that became Zimbabwe?", "answer": "<b> Rhodesia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A.P Hall was forced to withdrawal from this battle due to a bout of pericarditis. John Bell Hood lost the use of his left arm due to injuries sustained during this battle. Despite being advised against it by James Longstreet, 12,000 soldiers crossed Cemetery Ridge in this battle in a charge led by George Pickett. George Meade led Union forces in, for ten points, what 1863 defeat for Robert E. Lee in Pennsylvania, the turning point of the Civil War?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Gettysburg</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this event, a bannerman under En Hai assassinated German diplomat Clemens von Ketteler. In this conflict, foreign citizens were besieged for 55-days while taking refuge in the Legation Quarter. Sir Claude MacDonald commanded the Eight-Nation Alliance in response to this rebellion. During this rebellion, a provisional government was set-up in Tianjin to combat the Qing dynasty. The Righteous and Harmonious Fists launched, for ten points, what 1898 uprising against Western colonialism in China?", "answer": "<b> Boxer</b> Rebellion", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "\u201d Mount Davidson in Nevada was the site of an 1859 rush to the Comstock Lode, a massive find of this resource. For ten points, name this precious metal that could be exchanged at a fixed rate with a more precious metal in bimetallism.", "answer": "<b> silver</b> (prompt on mining)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The first Christian Mass in the Philippines was led by this explorer who was later ostracized after a falling out with King Manuel. This man died in a skirmish with the Lapu-Lapu on the island of Mactan. This explorer navigated a strait south of Chile during a lengthy expedition he led from the<em> La Trinidad</em>. For ten points, name this Portuguese sailor who led the first successful circumnavigation of the world.", "answer": "Ferdinand<b> Magellan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In one book, this philosopher argued that impressions and ideas were only different in terms of degree. The works of this philosopher awoke Immanuel Kant from his \u201cdogmatic slumber.\u201d This philosopher, who made the \u201cis-ought\u201d distinction and posited a missing shade of blue, wrote<em> Dialogues Concerning Natural</em> <em>Religion</em> and<em> A Treatise of Human Nature</em>. For ten points, name this Scottish empiricist, the author of<em> An</em> <em>Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding</em>.", "answer": "David<b> Hume</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Bob Dylan was controversially awarded this prize in 2016, on the basis that his lyrics were poetic.", "answer": "<b> Nobel</b> Prize in Literature <b></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>After losing the Battle of Stilo, a king of this name faced a rebellion called the Great Slav Uprising led by the Wendish people. With Conrad the Red, a king of this name ended</b> <b>the Magyar invasion of Bavaria by the chieftain (+)</b> <b>Bulcsu [BULL-choo] at a 955 battle.</b> <b>That king with this name agreed to be the secular protector of the Holy See, starting the (*)</b> Holy Roman Empire. For ten points, give this name of a \u201cGreat\u201d German king who was the son of Henry the Fowler and who defeated the Hungarians at Lechfeld.", "answer": "<b> Otto</b> (accept<b> Otto</b> the Great; accept<b> Otto</b> I, II, and/or III)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>To promote the London Underground, Horace Taylor created a poster of commuters on escalators in this artistic style. Hidden bars with mirror-topped tables were created in this style to conceal liquor during Prohibition. A street named for Benjamin Franklin is home to</b> <b>one of the earliest (+)</b> <b>buildings in this style created by Henri Sauvage in Paris. Another</b> <b>building designed in this style was decorated with radiator caps and gargoyles and, upon completion in (*)</b> 1931, surpassed the Empire State Building as the tallest building in the world. The Chrysler Building exemplifies, for ten points, what highly modern style that flourished in the 1920s?", "answer": "Art<b> Deco</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s wife organized private lectures with William Thackeray and Charles Dickens after creating the White House library. While trying to run for a 2nd term, this man lost</b> <b>the (+)</b> <b>Whig nomination to Winfield Scott. This President ordered Matthew Perry to</b> <b>open up (*)</b> Japan to western trade. In the Election of 1856, this man ran on the Know Nothing ticket but was soundly defeated by John C. Fremont and James Buchanan. For ten points, name this President who succeeded Zachary Taylor in 1850.", "answer": "Millard<b> Fillmore</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This conflict prompted CIA chief John Stockwell to resign after foreign troops invaded Shaba. A minor player in this conflict was the FLEC, a front for the liberation of Cabinda.</b> <b>This conflict became known as (+)</b> <b>\u201cCuba\u2019s Vietnam\u201d after the amount of aid that Fidel</b> <b>Castro sent to aid Agostinho Neto. This war finally ended when Jonas Savimbi was killed in (*)</b> 2002, ending 27 years of fighting that began when Portugal granted the country independence. The UNITA and MPLA factions fought in, for ten points, what civil war in southern Africa?", "answer": "<b> Angola</b>n Civil War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Magnus Carlsen is the current world champion of, for ten points, what centuries-old board game involving knights and rooks?", "answer": "<b> chess</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this country, a resistance cell led by Missak Manounchian was executed by the Secret</b> <b>Field Police. Josephine (+)</b> <b>Baker smuggled coded messages to this country from England</b> <b>by hiding them on her sheet music. An organization in this country that adopted the (*) </b>Lorraine Cross as their symbol sabotaged utilities and telecommunication networks in preparation for the Allied invasion of Normandy. For ten points, name this country where resistance cells fought Nazi occupation of cities like Paris.", "answer": "<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}